Hey, Izumi-kun.
Hej, Izumi-kun.
Did you hear about that incident,
Słyszałeś, że niedaleko zamordowano jakąś dziewczynę?
Oh, I heard about that!
Ja o tym słyszałam.
It's been making the rounds online!
Ciągle piszą o tym w sieci.
I heard you were the first one to find the victim, Izumi-kun!
Podobno to ty znalazłeś ofiarę, Izumi-kun.
Hey, Akiho!
Akiho!
You okay?
Wszystko gra?
Yeah. You?
Tak. A u ciebie?
I'm okay, too.
U mnie też.
So, um…
No to…
That day when we had planned to go see a movie…
W ten dzień, kiedy mieliśmy iść do kina…
It's awful when so many sad things happen.
Stało się ostatnio tyle okropnych rzeczy.
AUTHOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
AUTOR: HITOSHI IWAAKI
Regardless of all these dining locations we prepared,
Choć wyznaczyliśmy te punkty, w których mógł się pożywiać,
he intentionally fed outside of the designated areas
celowo żywił się w innych miejscach
and was killed.
i zginął.
An unfortunate incident, indeed.
Nieszczęśliwy incydent.
He gave in to the immediacy of hunger,
Stracił kontrolę nad głodem i stanął do walki z własnym gatunkiem.
How self-centered. Just like animals.
Egoizm. Zachował się jak zwierzę.
I'm glad he's dead.
Cieszę się, że zginął.
It's not that simple.
To nie takie proste.
The end result is that we have provided humans with another sample
Ludzie zdobyli kolejne ciało do zbadania,
and the perpetrator has yet to come forward.
a sprawca wciąż jest nieznany.
Could it have been the work of a human?
Czy mógł zrobić to człowiek?
Indeed.
Tak.
It was he who killed one of us.
To on zabił jednego z nas.
The boy who found the dead human.
Chłopiec, który znalazł ludzkie zwłoki.
Izumi Shinichi.
Izumi Shinichi.
He most likely snapped when he saw that his friend was murdered.
Stracił panowanie, gdy zamordowano jego przyjaciółkę.
"Friend"?
„Przyjaciółkę”? „Stracił panowanie”?
Is his brain entirely human?
Jego mózg jest w zupełności ludzki?
Yes.
Tak. Jego mózg pozostał niezmieniony.
and he is coexisting with his parasite.
Koegzystuje ze swoim pasożytem.
You could say that he is a valuable sample.
Jest dla nas wartościowym okazem.
A sample, huh?
Okazem, co?
He sounds like he could be a threat.
Wydaje się być raczej zagrożeniem.
I am making an effort to secure a better future for all of us.
Dbam o lepszą przyszłość dla nas wszystkich.
I ask you to consider my investigation of him as being a part of that endeavor.
I w ramach tych starań pragnę przyjrzeć się mu bliżej.
Very well.
W porządku.
I'll leave the matter of the boy to you.
Pozostawiam tego chłopca pani.
By the way, Tamura-san, how is your child?
A jak tam pani dziecko, Tamura-san?
It is living a normal life,
Ma normalne życie,
although I am rearing it with human assistance.
choć wychowuję je z ludzką pomocą.
Oh my.
Ojej.
There.
Już, już.
What's the matter?
Co się stało?
I've changed your diaper.
Już cię przewinęłam.
Oh, it's Mommy.
O, jest mamusia.
Hello. Welcome back.
Witamy w domu.
Quiet.
Ucisz się.
I have it trained well, don't I?
Dobrze go wyszkoliłam, co?
Thank you for the help.
Dziękuję za pomoc.
Please come again tomorrow.
Proszę wrócić jutro.
Of course.
Oczywiście.
I… I'll be going, then!
To… ja już pójdę.
If I were to conduct an experiment of some kind,
Jeśli miałabym przeprowadzić jakiś eksperyment,
I would first need to let it grow a bit more.
wpierw musi podrosnąć.
I investigated for a solid week but found nothing out of the ordinary.
Po tygodniu obserwacji nie znalazłem niczego niezwykłego.
It's of interest that his mother has gone missing
Poza tym, że jego matka zaginęła
and that he's a witness in the high school girl's murder,
i że był świadkiem morderstwa uczennicy,
but he's truly just an average high school student.
to całkowicie zwyczajny licealista.
Yes, that's right.
Tak, zgadza się.
I understand.
Rozumiem.
Please continue your investigation.
Proszę kontynuować śledztwo.
An "average high school student", huh?
Zwyczajny licealista, co?
Human powers of observation are less than impressive.
Ludzie nie są zbyt spostrzegawczy.
However, there are some things only humans are capable of.
Jednak pewne rzeczy mogą zrobić tylko oni.
I could not test him using Shimada Hideo,
Shimada Hideo nie mógł go dla mnie sprawdzić,
but perhaps I'll try something.
ale mogę sama spróbować.
Izumi Shinichi, right?
Izumi Shinichi?
Who put you up to this?
Kto was na mnie nasłał?
A… A woman.
Jakaś kobieta.
A woman?
Kobieta? Jak się nazywa?
Don't know. Just met her today for the first time.
Nie wiem. Poznaliśmy ją dopiero wczoraj.
It's the truth!
Mówię prawdę!
Yo.
Hej.
Kamijo.
Kamijo.
Why the gloomy face so early in the morning?
Coś ty taki ponury z samego rana?
It's not gloomy.
Nie jestem ponury.
Things going well with your girlfriend?
A jak się układa z dziewczyną?
What things?
- Z dziewczyną? - Nie zgrywaj głupka.
You know what I mean.
Wiesz, o czym mówię.
Cut it out!
Przestań.
Nothing like that's going on.
Niczego między nami nie ma.
Stop joking around.
Przestań żartować.
So, I don't really want to get into this,
Nie chciałam się w to mieszać,
but you've heard about Izumi-kun, right?
ale słyszałaś o Izumi-kunie, prawda?
I heard he was the first one to find the victim in the recent murder
Podobno to on znalazł tę zamordowaną dziewczynę
and he knew the girl who was killed.
i znał ją osobiście.
Yeah, I know.
Wiem o tym.
What about it?
I co?
Did your brother say something?
Twój brat coś mówił?
Not really.
W sumie to nie.
It's just that, even though something like that happened,
Po prostu dziwię się, że jest po tym wszystkim taki spokojny.
He's acting too normal.
Zachowuje się tak normalnie.
Morning.
Dzień dobry.
Bye, Satomi.
Cześć, Satomi.
What's up with her?
Co z nią?
Nothing.
Nic.
Back when he saved my life,
Kiedy ratował mi życie,
he was also so calm and strong.
był taki opanowany i silny.
It was like he was someone else.
Jakby był kimś innym.
But was there really nothing going on between him and Kana?
Czy między nim i Kaną naprawdę nic nie było?
No, that's not the point.
Zresztą nie o to chodzi.
Even if nothing was going on, isn't he being a bit cold about all this?
Jest za spokojny, nawet jeśli nic ich nie łączyło.
Murano?
Murano?
Sorry, I have to go take care of something.
Przepraszam. Muszę iść coś załatwić.
Well, it sure was a shock to see how fast he could move.
Byłem zdumiony, jaki jest szybki.
I can hardly believe he's human.
Trudno uwierzyć, że to człowiek.
And?
I?
Did you notice anything else?
Zauważył pan coś jeszcze?
What do you mean by that?
To znaczy?
Well, did anything else seem unnatural?
Czy coś wydawało się panu nienaturalne?
Was his right hand moving in a peculiar way, for example?
Czy jego prawa dłoń poruszała się w dziwny sposób?
Let me think.
Pomyślmy.
No. Nothing really stood out.
Nie, nic takiego.
So some other specific change must have occurred.
Więc musiała zajść jakaś inna zmiana.
I wonder what's wrong.
Ciekawe, co jest nie tak.
Maybe what happened to Kana is getting to Murano.
Najwyraźniej Murano mocno przeżywa to, co stało się z Kaną.
Yeah, of course it is.
Tak, oczywiście. To zrozumiałe, że się przejęła.
Considering what happened,
Po tym, co się stało,
I'm the one who's strange for being so calm about it.
to ja jestem dziwakiem, zachowując spokój.
It's not normal.
To nienormalne.
What are you going on about now?
Co ty znowu gadasz?
You're a perfectly fine human being.
Jesteś normalnym człowiekiem.
You are not like me or my kind.
Nie jesteś jak ja.
Hearing you say that makes me lose even more confidence in myself.
Po tych słowach czuję się jeszcze mniej pewnie.
Either way, our conversation is generating a certain amount of noise.
Ludzie mogą usłyszeć, jak ze mną rozmawiasz.
If you talk out loud on top of that,
Kiedy podnosisz na mnie głos,
your father will become suspicious of all the noise.
twój ojciec staje się podejrzliwy.
Dad,
Tato.
I'm going out for a bit.
Wychodzę na trochę.
Don't stay out too late.
Nie wracaj za późno.
Where's he off to at this time of night?
A on dokąd o tej porze?
If I recall,
To w tym miejscu zamordowano tamtą dziewczynę.
Why would the first one to find the victim go back to the crime scene?
A on znalazł jej ciało. Czemu tam wraca?
There's something going on.
Coś tu jest nie tak.
Given his actions earlier today and what he's doing now,
Zwłaszcza uwzględniając to, co robił wcześniej.
Izumi Shinichi has a big secret!
Izumi Shinichi coś skrywa.
Shinichi, why are we here?
Shinichi, co tu robimy?
I can't explain it well,
Nie potrafię tego wyjaśnić,
that I now tend to forget painful or sad things really quickly.
ale chyba faktycznie bardzo szybko zapominam bolesne i smutne przeżycia.
And is that wrong?
To coś złego?
I wasn't like this before.
Wcześniej taki nie byłem.
I used to obsess over the smallest things and worry all the time.
Zamartwiałem się przez najmniejsze drobiazgi.
Now, that's what I would call a waste of time.
To dopiero strata czasu.
That's not what I mean!
Nie w tym rzecz.
Who is he talking to?
Z kim on gada?
Himself?
Ze sobą?
I think Kana approached that monster because she mistakenly thought it was me
Myślę, że Kana podeszła do tego potwora, bo wzięła go za mnie.
and it got her killed.
I dlatego zginęła.
Because of me!
Przeze mnie.
You should stop thinking like that.
Przestań tak myśleć.
No, for her, I want to…
Nie. Chciałbym…
This might be a strange way to put it,
To może dziwnie zabrzmieć,
but I want to mourn her death more.
ale chciałbym czuć większy żal po jej śmierci.
I don't want to forget how sad it makes me feel
Nie chcę zapomnieć tego smutku.
as a human being.
To on czyni mnie człowiekiem.
Monster!
Potwór!
Migi! What are you trying to do?
Migi, co ty wyprawiasz?
What else? I'm going to kill him!
A jak myślisz? Zabiję go.
Wait! Stop!
Co? Nie!
Get out of here! Hurry!
Uciekaj stąd!
Shinichi! Don't interfere!
Nie wtrącaj się.
What are you doing? Run!
Szybko, uciekaj!
I don't have sufficient weight to slice him in half.
Brak mi masy, by przeciąć go na pół.
Not good. If he gets any further away…
Niedobrze. Jeśli bardziej się oddali…
Someone, help!
Pomocy!
Migi.
Migi.
Hey!
Zdajesz sobie sprawę, w jakiej jesteś sytuacji?
We've been seen by a total stranger!
Zobaczył nas ktoś obcy.
With a camera, no less!
I miał przy sobie kamerę.
Run! Follow him!
Musimy go dogonić.
And kill him!
I zabić.
No, we can't kill him!
Nie możemy go zabić.
Migi, stop it!
Migi, zatrzymaj się!
Many humans in your vicinity have already died.
W twojej obecności zginęło już wiele osób.
What's one more death?
Co zmieni ta jedna śmierć?
It's to protect ourselves, no less.
Zwłaszcza że to dla naszego bezpieczeństwa.
There is no reason to hesitate!
Nie ma się co zastanawiać.
I said "no"!
Powiedziałem, nie!
We can't do this!
Nie możemy tego zrobić!
I'm tired.
Zmęczyłem się.
We can't kill a human being,
Nie możemy zabijać ludzi
no matter what the reason!
z jakiegokolwiek powodu.
He got away.
Uciekł.
It's too late to catch up with him now.
Już go nie dogonimy.
You took a while.
Długo cię nie było.
Did something happen?
Czy coś się stało?
No.
Nie.
Nothing happened.
Nic się nie stało.
I hope not.
Mam nadzieję.
That male
Ten mężczyzna bacznie cię obserwował.
It means that although he knows a lot about us,
A choć on wie o nas tak wiele,
we know nothing about him.
my nie wiemy o nim absolutnie nic.
If he's a journalist
Jeśli jest dziennikarzem, policjantem
We will become lab rats, without a doubt.
Skończymy jak myszy laboratoryjne.
Lab rats.
Myszy laboratoryjne.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun.
You monster!
Ty potworze!
Did you eat people?
Pożerasz ludzi?
Stay away from me!
Nie zbliżaj się!
Izumi Shinichi is a parasite!
Izumi Shinichi to pasożyt!
What, Izumi?
- Co? Izumi? - Izumi?
Izumi!
Izumi!
Hey, Izumi!
Hej, Izumi!
Read the next page. Weren't you listening?
Przeczytaj następną stronę.
Sheesh.
Jeśli nie chcesz tu być, to wracaj do domu.
Izumi!
Izumi!
Hey, he actually left.
Naprawdę wyszedł.
Izumi-kun.
Izumi-kun,
They'll come.
Przyjdą.
I'm sure of it.
Na pewno.
Someone will come to make me into a lab rat.
Ktoś przyjdzie i zrobi ze mnie mysz laboratoryjną.
But before that happens, one of my kind may terminate us.
A wcześniej może dopaść nas ktoś z mojego gatunku.
Either way, we will suffer consequences.
Tak czy inaczej, czekają nas konsekwencje.
What should I…
Co mam zrobić?
Maybe if I cut off this arm now while Migi's asleep…
Może jeśli odetnę sobie dłoń, kiedy Migi będzie spał…
As if I could do that.
Nie mógłbym tego zrobić.
Who was he?
Kim on był?
Who's after me?
Kto chce mnie dopaść?
After us?
A raczej nas.
Could he still be watching us today, right now?
Być może przygląda nam się właśnie w tej chwili.
Mom, this way!
Mamo, tutaj!
Wait, Saki-chan.
Poczekaj, Saki-chan.
Moving on to traffic updates.
A teraz raport drogowy…
Delivery!
Dostawa!
Wait! Listen!
Nie! Posłuchaj!
Please, hear me out!
Wysłuchaj mnie!
Why?
Dlaczego?
Why is this happening?
Dlaczego to się dzieje?
Why is all this happening to me?
Dlaczego mi się to przytrafia?
I can always calm down right away.
Mogę uspokoić się w mgnieniu oka.
That's how my heart works now.
Moje serce zmieniło się.
There's no going back now.
Nie ma już odwrotu.
If that's the case, I might as well…
W takim razie mogę…
What's wrong? Why did you ask to see me out of the blue?
Dlaczego mnie tu tak nagle zaprosiłeś?
Well…
Chodzi o Tachikawę.
I mean…
Znów jest wesoła jak wcześniej.
and she managed to avoid getting a scar on her face.
I nawet nie została jej blizna na twarzy.
You called me out here just to say that?
Umówiłeś się tu ze mną, żeby to powiedzieć?
Oh, not really.
Niezupełnie.
I wanted to talk to you, that's all.
Po prostu chciałem pogadać.
It's like you don't expect us to meet again.
Zachowujesz się, jakbyśmy mieli się już nie zobaczyć.
That's not true.
Nieprawda.
Izumi-kun, you seem like your mind is muddled.
Izumi-kun jesteś jakiś nieswój.
I feel kind of muddled, too, actually .
Ja zresztą też czuję się nieswojo.
Can I start?
Mogę zacząć?
Sure.
Proszę.
I've been trying not to dwell on it,
Wolałam tego nie rozpamiętywać,
but I can't help myself.
ale nic na to nie poradzę.
It's about Kana-san.
Chodzi mi o Kanę-san.
You canceled our date that day to go meet with Kana-san, right?
Tamtego dnia odwołałeś naszą randkę, żeby się z nią zobaczyć, prawda?
It must've been important.
To musiało być coś ważnego.
At least, more important than seeing a movie with me.
A przynajmniej ważniejszego niż pójście ze mną do kina.
I've been wanting to talk to you about a lot of things, but--
Chciałem z tobą porozmawiać, ale…
Why don't you?
Ale co?
Why don't you tell me everything? You should just tell me everything!
Powinieneś mi wszystko powiedzieć.
Izumi-kun, something has been bothering you, right?
Izumi-kun, coś cię gryzie, prawda?
Something besides the thing with Kana-san.
Coś oprócz tej sprawy z Kaną-san.
That's not…
Ja nie…
I can tell!
Przecież widzę!
It's got you so worried
Tak się czymś zamartwiasz,
that not even someone dying
że nawet czyjaś śmierć
That's…
Nie…
That's not true.
Nieprawda.
Izumi-kun, you're strong.
Izumi-kun, jesteś silny.
You're really strong.
Bardzo silny.
But sometimes, I can barely stand to watch you.
Ale czasem nie mogę nawet na ciebie patrzeć.
You're so desperate to keep something in check.
Widzę, że zmagasz się z czymś.
So, what happened?
Co naprawdę się stało?
Don't try so hard to go it alone. Talk to me.
Nie zmagaj się z tym sam. Porozmawiaj ze mną.
Murano.
Murano.
Nothing!
Nie, nic się nie stało.
How can I believe that nothing's going on?
Jak możesz tak myśleć?
I can't even talk to you if you're going to be like this!
Jeśli masz się tak zachowywać, to nie mamy o czym gadać.
Don't say that.
Nie mów tak.
If even you say that to me, I…
Jeśli nawet ty masz mnie tak traktować,
I… I'll tell you!
to wszystko ci powiem.
I'll tell you, okay?
Powiem ci.
Satomi!
Satomi!
My body…
Moje ciało…
My body has a…
Moje ciało jest…
Seriously, nothing's going on.
Serio, nic się nie dzieje.
I guess you don't trust me at all.
Najwyraźniej mi nie ufasz.
I can't do anything about the fact that you won't believe me.
Nic nie poradzę na to, że mi nie wierzysz.
Izumi-kun, your eyes, they're so empty.
Izumi-kun, twoje oczy są takie puste.
Next time, "The Selfish Gene."
Następny odcinek: „Samolubny gen”